<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ahmed Al-Bahar]]></title>
  <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-23T17:24:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ahmed Al-Bahar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is Devbootcamp?]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/what-is-devbootcamp/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T16:40:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/what-is-devbootcamp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.devbootcamp.com" target="_blank">Dev Bootcamp</a> is one of the first programming bootcamps to crop up since its inception in 2012. There are now over 50 such bootcamps across the country.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://s3-media3.fl.yelpcdn.com/bphoto/Vml6x1otS8vzAbEoNfNPDA/l.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p><strong>Was It Worth It?</strong></p>

<p>For me personally, I found Dev Bootcamp to be a great investment.</p>

<p>Coming out of the program I have now have over 1000 hours of coding with over 500 hours dedicated to pair coding over a period of 18 weeks (9 weeks full time and 9 weeks part time).</p>

<p>Dev Bootcamp is focused around Ruby and Rails with time spent on HTML, CSS, Javascript, JQuery with significant time getting familiar with testing frameworks like RSpec and Jasmine as well as heavily utilizing git workflow.</p>

<p>The specific languages and frameworks covered are not too important though, the real value from Dev Bootcamp is learning how to learn new tech.</p>

<p>For example, in our final 8 day project we were able to integrate</p>

<ul>
<li>an iOS app built with Swift</li>
<li>a Ruby on Rails web app interface</li>
<li>a public rails API</li>
<li>an integration with Amazon S3 for real time storage</li>
<li>with the web app deployed on Heroku</li>
</ul>


<p>with creating APIs, Swift and S3 integration not part of the Dev Bootcamp curriculum.</p>

<p><strong>How is the Dev Bootcamp Environment?</strong></p>

<p>The Chicago Dev Bootcamp location is quite nice. Coding, while a big part of Dev Bootcamp is not the only thing we do from 8 a.m to 7-9 p.m.</p>

<ul>
<li>Yoga sessions twice a week in phase 1 (once a week in phase 2 &amp; 3)</li>
<li>Engineering empathy sessions once a week in phase 1 &amp; 2</li>
<li>Thursday speaker series every Thursday at 5:30 p.m</li>
<li>Design lunch series every Wednesday at 12:00 p.m</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why did you decide to go to Dev Bootcamp if your going Business School?</strong></p>

<p>The main reason for applying to business school is to transition to the tech industry. Spending the time upfront and getting a good foundation prior to attending MIT Sloan&rsquo;s business school will allow me to cross register at the Computer Science department as well as be involved in building new products at entrepreneurship competitions and hackathons on campus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I decided to start blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/why-i-decided-to-start-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T14:38:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/why-i-decided-to-start-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After Graduating from <a href="http://www.devbootcamp.com" target="_blank">Dev Bootcamp</a> a couple of weeks ago, I find myself at loss for words and I feel this blog will not only serve as a vehicle for self reflection but also be a way for me to document my experiences working my way through the MIT Sloan MBA program for the next 2 years.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/ZYJSWkk.jpg/ width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>Some major themes I hope to cover include:
* Career journey transitioning to the tech industry
* Fumbling my way to coding fluency
* Higher Education thoughts and experiences</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
