<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ahmed Al-Bahar]]></title>
  <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-28T14:33:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ahmed Al-Bahar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My visit to TableXI]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/24/my-visit-to-tablexi/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T19:13:13-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/24/my-visit-to-tablexi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/jmozen" target="_blank">Jen Mozen</a> and everyone at <a href="http://www.tablexi.com/" target="_blank">Table XI</a> for inviting me to their lunch talk series and for showing me around the work space!</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/nCY7SOB.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>Table XI is a development firm that works with startups and midstage companies to help them build products or to help serve as a defacto CTO for firms in need for tech expertise.</p>

<p><strong>How was the atmosphere?</strong></p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/3db78s4.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>I found the atmosphere at Table XI to be nice and open. I enjoyed the open space layout but I also felt employees were able to really get down and focus on their work at the same time with the help of headphones and the right tunes.</p>

<p><strong>How does Table XI like to work?</strong></p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/B8S5ayT.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>The Table XI team is comprised of over 30 employees and work in small teams of 4-5 co-currently on multiple projects at the same time. The small teams change up every 5-6 weeks.</p>

<p>Table XI has a full kitchen and offers employees free lunch daily. Lunch is very social at Table XI and I can tell from my visit that everyone has a lot of fun working with one another.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/Ey2GKRU.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>PS. The food was delicous!</p>

<p><strong>What tech does Table XI currently work with?</strong></p>

<p>I did not get much of a chance to discuss the tech that Table XI most commonly works with but I do know ruby and rails is a part of their tech arsenel. You can read more about tech challenges that Table XI face via their <a href="http://www.tablexi.com/blog/" target="_blank">blog</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Final thoughts</strong></p>

<p>I found Table XI to be a very warm environment with a strong focus on a good work life balance. The leadership at Table XI are very approachable which was a nice experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My visit to Steelseries]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/24/my-visit-to-steelseries/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T17:04:19-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/24/my-visit-to-steelseries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been a big fan of <a href="http://steelseries.com/" target="_blank">Steelseries</a>, a gaming gear manufacturer, since I was in high school back in 2002/2003 with the heavy use of their hard plastic gaming mouse pads.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/A9mCcsp.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p><a href="https://twitter.com/dastels" target="_blank">Dave Astels</a> was kind enough to give me a tour of the Steelseries location based in Chicago.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/3uT7WiS.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p><strong>How was the atmosphere?</strong></p>

<p>I found the atmosphere at Steelseries to be quite appropriate for a game peripheral design and manufacturing firm. Each Steelseries engineer had their own neat personal flare on their desks and the walls are adorned with some of our favorite gaming icons.</p>

<p><strong>How does Steelseries like to work?</strong></p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/d0Tc7Xp.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>From what I gathered from my visit, it looks like the development team works on one project at a time with a kaban process management approach utilized.</p>

<p>Some of the quicker projects such as re-branding a peripheral for a specific game or event can take 1 to 2 days while more complex projects coding projects can take as long as 3-4 months.</p>

<p><strong>What tech does Steelseries currently work with?</strong></p>

<p>Steelseries recently rebuild the foundation of their codebase using <a href="http://golang.org/" target="_blank">Go</a> with the front user facing application build using javascript/css/html with some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)" target="_blank">Lisp</a> interaction to interface with the gaming hardware and sqlite database to store some peripheral specific data. Steelseries Lisp codebase is opensource for those of you interested!</p>

<p><strong>Final thoughts</strong></p>

<p>With co-worker gaming nights on Fridays, gaming breaks in the office and an employee Donkey Kong high score list proudly noted in one of the team office rooms, Steelseries looks like a developer&rsquo;s gaming haven.</p>

<p>PS. Big thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/dastels" target="_blank">Dave</a> for great parting <a href="http://steelseries.com/us/products/mice/steelseries-rival" target="_blank">gift</a>! Gaming mice have gotten so much better since my serious gaming days a decade ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is Devbootcamp?]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/what-is-devbootcamp/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T16:40:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/what-is-devbootcamp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.devbootcamp.com" target="_blank">Dev Bootcamp</a> is one of the first programming bootcamps to crop up since its inception in 2012. There are now over 50 such bootcamps across the country.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://s3-media3.fl.yelpcdn.com/bphoto/Vml6x1otS8vzAbEoNfNPDA/l.jpg width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p><strong>Was It Worth It?</strong></p>

<p>For me personally, I found Dev Bootcamp to be a great investment.</p>

<p>Coming out of the program I have now have over 1000 hours of coding with over 500 hours dedicated to pair coding over a period of 18 weeks (9 weeks full time and 9 weeks part time).</p>

<p>Dev Bootcamp is focused around Ruby and Rails with time spent on HTML, CSS, Javascript, JQuery with significant time getting familiar with testing frameworks like RSpec and Jasmine as well as heavily utilizing git workflow.</p>

<p>The specific languages and frameworks covered are not too important though, the real value from Dev Bootcamp is learning how to learn new tech.</p>

<p>For example, in our final 8 day project we were able to integrate</p>

<ul>
<li>an iOS app built with Swift</li>
<li>a Ruby on Rails web app interface</li>
<li>a public rails API</li>
<li>an integration with Amazon S3 for real time storage</li>
<li>with the web app deployed on Heroku</li>
</ul>


<p>with creating APIs, Swift and S3 integration not part of the Dev Bootcamp curriculum.</p>

<p><strong>How is the Dev Bootcamp Environment?</strong></p>

<p>The Chicago Dev Bootcamp location is quite nice. Coding, while a big part of Dev Bootcamp is not the only thing we do from 8 a.m to 7-9 p.m.</p>

<ul>
<li>Yoga sessions twice a week in phase 1 (once a week in phase 2 &amp; 3)</li>
<li>Engineering empathy sessions once a week in phase 1 &amp; 2</li>
<li>Thursday speaker series every Thursday at 5:30 p.m</li>
<li>Design lunch series every Wednesday at 12:00 p.m</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why did you decide to go to Dev Bootcamp if your going Business School?</strong></p>

<p>The main reason for applying to business school is to transition to the tech industry. Spending the time upfront and getting a good foundation prior to attending MIT Sloan&rsquo;s business school will allow me to cross register at the Computer Science department as well as be involved in building new products at entrepreneurship competitions and hackathons on campus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I decided to start blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/why-i-decided-to-start-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T14:38:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ahmedalbahar.com/blog/2014/07/23/why-i-decided-to-start-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After Graduating from <a href="http://www.devbootcamp.com" target="_blank">Dev Bootcamp</a> a couple of weeks ago, I find myself at loss for words and I feel this blog will not only serve as a vehicle for self reflection but also be a way for me to document my experiences working my way through the MIT Sloan MBA program for the next 2 years.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src = http://i.imgur.com/ZYJSWkk.jpg/ width="450" height="450" >
</p>


<p>Some major themes I hope to cover include:
* Career journey transitioning to the tech industry
* Fumbling my way to coding fluency
* Higher Education thoughts and experiences</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
